<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Wonders from the deep, or, A true and exact account and description of the monstrous whale lately taken near Colchester, being two and forty foot in length, and of bigness proportionable, with the manner of its coming, and being kill'd on Thursday the 9th of April, being so rare and strange a sight that multitudes of people from all parts dayly go to see it as thick as to a market or fair.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66921</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3378A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20746</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12735127</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12735127</idno>
            <idno type="VID">92997</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66921)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 92997)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 994:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Wonders from the deep, or, A true and exact account and description of the monstrous whale lately taken near Colchester, being two and forty foot in length, and of bigness proportionable, with the manner of its coming, and being kill'd on Thursday the 9th of April, being so rare and strange a sight that multitudes of people from all parts dayly go to see it as thick as to a market or fair.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for E.W.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Whales --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:92997:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 107 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:92997:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 107 -->
            <p>WONDERS From the Deep OR A True and Exact Account and Deſcription OF THE Monſtrous Whale, Lately taken near COLECHESTER, Being two and forty Foot in Length, and of Bigneſs Proportionable.</p>
            <p>With the manner of its coming, and being Kill'd on <hi>Thurſday</hi> the 9th. of <hi>April.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being ſo rare and ſtrange a ſight that mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of People from all parts dayly go to ſee it as thick as to a Market or Fair.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of fish</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed for <hi>E. W.</hi> in the Year 1677.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:92997:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 108 -->
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:92997:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 108 -->
            <head>Wonders from the Deep, or a true and exact Account, and Diſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Monſtrous Whale, late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken near Colcheſter, &amp;.</head>
            <p>WHen the Breath of Omnipotency gave by his Divine word a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the univerſe as he beautified the Chambers of the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, with glittering Stars, the Earth with Beaſts, Herbs, and Flowers, ſo he alſo endued the Waters with a prolifick quallity, and Stocks the Sea with ſuch a Strange Variety of its own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions, that 'tis affirmed by ſome of the Learned, that the Land can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not boaſt any ſort of Animal, but the Ocean can ſhow ſomewhat Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logous or reſemblant.</p>
            <p>But amongſt all the wonders of the Deep, that which moſt Summons our Admiration, Is <hi>the Whale,</hi> that floating Caſtle, or Natural ſhip, of ſo vaſt a Bulk as would make an Ignorant martinet miſtake it for an Iſland; True it is theſe Princes of the Watry Realm, but I know not what kind of inſtinct, delight cheifly to keep their Court near the North-Pole, and rarely Wonder far from the Artick Circle; very ſeldome, ſcarce once in diverſe Ages have one of them been known in our Seas, whence ſome ſuperſtitious People would make it a Prodigy, but ſince neighther Scripture nor Phyloſophy, Reaſon nor Senſe Countenance ſuch a Conceit, I muſt (with their pardon) call all their pretended Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riences, Dotages of Melancholy, and abuſes, <hi>Non cauſa Pro cauſâ,</hi> no more to be heeded than the Salts falling or a Hares Croſſing out of the way, and the like reverend obſervations of my <hi>Grannum;</hi> but waving this, perhaps to ſome diſreliſhing diſcourſe that our Brittiſh Channel has late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been honoured with one of theſe ſtranger gueſts, for on <hi>Thurſday</hi> the 19. of this Inſtant <hi>April,</hi> between <hi>Tueſe<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>VVotton,</hi> two ſmall places about four miles from each other in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and about a dozen or fourteen miles from <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> the winds having blown hard for ſeveral days before, A <hi>VVhale</hi> was brought in with the Tide, but being got into a kind of Narrow Creek when the Water fell, he could not get out again, but remained there upon the ſhallows, beating himſelf all that Ebb and till the next full Sea, but had before ſo weakned and diſabled himſelf that he could not then neither get off, in this time being juſt on the ſhore he was ſeen by divers Country people with no ſmall Admiration, having never before ſeen a Creature of ſo vaſt a Bulk,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:92997:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 109 -->on the ſecond day it was alive, being driven near a Rock or at leaſt a ſtony Bank, the violence of its Agitation and ſtriving in ſhort time Kill'd it, and prevented the Tryumph, ſome Fiſhermen thereabout promiſed themſelves, who immagined no leſs Glory by murthering of it, then St. <hi>George</hi> did by the deſtruction of the Dragon.</p>
            <p>After it was dead the Tyde being out, the Dimenſions of it were taken, and tis Certainly found to be in length two and forty foot, and in Bigneſs evry way anſwerable, with faſtning Ropes to it, and with ſeveral Teems the Country-men hald it to ſhore, where it now remains the grand wonder and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of all thoſe parts, People comming every day to ſee it in multitudes as if they were going to a Market or Fair.</p>
            <p>Near twenty Years ago about the ſame place was diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and taken an Extroardinary <hi>Fiſh,</hi> not only for its bigneſs but alſo its ſhape, which was ſo prodigious and unuſual that none though never ſo much accuſtomed to the Seas, could tell its name or remember to have ſeen the like.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that would ſee a diſcription of this wonderful Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture called a <hi>Whale</hi> and its nature, may find it incomparably drawn by a Divine pencill in the one and fortieth <hi>Chapter</hi> of <hi>Job.</hi> under the Name of <hi>Leviathan,</hi> to which I refer the pious Reader and their with conclude with this Relation, of the truth whereof if any be diſſatisfied, the <hi>Colcheſter</hi> Carriers at the <hi>Kings Arms</hi> in <hi>Leaden-Hall-ſtreet,</hi> and the <hi>Croſs-Keys</hi> in <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtreet,</hi> can and will be ready fully to inform them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
